Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to be
learning how to memorize the polyatomics.
Now the polyatomic ions, the best
way to memorize them is sometimes
to just simply use flashcards, but
sometimes we don't have the luxury of
being able to remember all of them.
I'm going to teach you today the T43
method, which is something that you can
easily be able to find just by having
a periodic table, which is Generally,
the only thing you are allowed to have
on a lot of Chem 3A or Chem 1A or any,
or whatever level of chemistry exams.
So um, let's get into it.
So the whole idea here is what
exactly are the polyatomics?
Well these are your oxyanions,
meaning they are all these different
species where there's a nonmetal
that's bound to multiple oxygens.
Now these different species, they
always exist in the exact same unit.
Meaning that this, let's say if I have
this CO3 here, it's always going to
be bound together and it's all, the
entire thing has a two minus charge.
So every single time has the same
charge, same number of oxygens,
and we treat it like an anion.
Now, the easy way to try to do these is,
first is, I recommend just memorizing
the eight ions, which are the ones
that have the most number of oxygens.
for the majority of the polyatomics.
Now, flashcards do help with trying
to memorize these, but it's easy to
forget and sometimes you get stressed
and anxious and you don't remember.
But there's a hidden trend in your
periodic table for this method.
Now I did not come up with this method.
It's one that I kind of picked up from
my students finding things on YouTube.
And it is very, very helpful
if you are confident in it.
So let me show you where it is.
So it all starts with looking at
the periodic table right here.
So what we have here is we can
actually spell out the letters T,
4, and 3 when you look at this.
So we see a T, 4, 3.
And what the whole idea here is by
spelling this out in this exact pattern.
It tells you the number of
oxygens for each of these species.
So what we're going to do here
is on the next, next part, we're
going to look at each one of these.
We're going to analyze them and
assign exactly how we can memorize
this so that way we can remember
it very quickly and on the fly so
that way you're quicker on an exam.
You don't want to be bogged down.
You want to know it fast.
Um, now every single teacher
is a little bit different.
Sometimes they will give you reference
sheets to know your polyatomics, maybe
on the first exam or the second one.
But most of them, especially if you're
taking chem, depending on your level
of chemistry, They will eventually
expect you to know them by the end of
the semester, and definitely if you are
a science major who has to take harder
courses, you will need to know this.
For health science majors, typically you
need to know this because the polyatomics
are something that is very prevalent in
a lot of health science applications.
Um, such as a medicines or maybe
something that's like used in different
plastics or casts or all kinds of
different, different things that you
find laying around and even allow
your food and nutrition items as well.
It's all around us, so let's
take a look this method.
All
right, so I recopied our T4 3 from our
periodic table and I put down all the
elements that are here that make up
those and I color coded them to match.
Now the key here is what the let,
what the T43 represents is the number
of oxygens that each one of these
different species present, or have.
So if you have T, that means
that you have, uh, three.
If you have the number 4, that means
4, and then the number 3 means 3.
So, what we're going to do here
is we're going to fill in all
these little missing pieces.
So we'll start over here on the
chlorates, and bromates, and iodates,
and we will fill in all the charges.
And we go over to sulfate, and
selenite, and tellurite, tellurate.
You can see that we also have all of
our individual, um, pieces as well.
So same with like phosphate and arsenate.
Then with nitrate, we can see that
we have three same with carbonate,
uh, siliconate and borate.
We have each one of those that
matches the number that we have.
Now, what about the charges?
The good thing is here is the charges
actually, for the most part, go
with the periodic table trends.
So if you remember for, for the
halogens, right, that's negative
one, for sulfur, that's negative two.
So we can fill in the same
charges for those columns.
So we're gonna put the negative one
next to the chlorates, bromates.
Negative two next to the, to
the sulfates and cell selenites
or selenites and tolerates.
Now with nitrate and below, this
is where it's a little different.
So phosphate and arsenate are still
three minus, they go off the rule,
but things kind of like reset on
the, uh, T area, which I realize
this is missile colored here.
So on t we kind of, uh, reset our trend.
So, nitrate is negative 1, carbonate is
negative 2, and then borate is negative 3.
So it sort of goes backwards
in order as we're going through
these different trends, okay?
So this is how you can quickly
be able to memorize them.
It goes off your periodic table
trends, or ion charges, and you
can use a T4 3 to quickly be able
to know how many ionic charges.
I hope that this video helped.
Please hit that like and
subscribe button if it did.
I hope that this will help you be
able to better understand how to
memorize different polyatomic ions.
And please check out my other
chemistry videos to better further
your understanding of chemistry.
Thank you so much for watching.
Bye now.